<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Counter-votes: or, an arraignment, and conviction of the votes at Oxford.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80676</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868844</idno>
  <idno type="VID">154435</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240955804</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6523</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E42_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210002</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868844</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99868844e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80676)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154435)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E42[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Counter-votes: or, an arraignment, and conviction of the votes at Oxford.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed according to order for Matthew Walbancke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon as transcribed by Madan.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 10th 1644".</note>
                  <note>A commentary on the proceedings of the Oxford Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; cropped at foot, affecting text, including colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Great Britain. --  Parliament. --  House of Commons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154435:1"/>
            <head>COVNTER-VOTES: OR, AN <hi>ARRAIGNMENT,</hi> AND <hi>CONVICTION</hi> OF THE VOTES AT OXFORD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>EFORE I enter upon the <hi>Votes</hi> or <hi>Resultes</hi> of that Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell at <hi>Oxford,</hi> it will be wisdom to inquire, what they are, what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they have, or from whom, that made them; Whether that they are, or were the Members of this present Parliament here at <hi>Westminster;</hi> whether they were convented anew by the King, or Assembled themselves together without any calling. If they are the old Members (which for their Rottennesse were rescinded least they should destroy the whole body) then no Members of this Parliament; for a Member cutt off, is no part of the body: Therefore the King could not in persuance of that Act made this present Parliament, adjourne the Parliament to <hi>Oxford</hi> by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent. If they be a new Convention, why yet no Parliament, for that were to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve the Parliament here at <hi>Westminster</hi> without their consent, which His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty hath bound himselfe from by that Act (if Acts of Parliament binde them at <hi>Oxford.</hi>) And therefore it is Resolved upon the question, and this <hi>Nemine contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicente</hi> too, that that Assembly or Juncto at <hi>Oxford</hi> (Baptise it by what name you will) is a meere Convention of private men, who have assembled themselves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the behalfe of the King and Kingdome, to Vote point blancke against the peace and happinesse of both.</p>
            <p>Hence learne true Subject that <hi>Oxford</hi> Votes (especially if Her Majesty be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent) doe not binde thee to Obedience. Therefore exchange not your money or Plate for Privie Seales (which carry no better credit then formerly) without you would be Voted out of all your substance. The truth is, they have already Voted you out of your Religion, Lives, Liberties, and Estates; and (if you bee not the more vigilant) will are long, vote you out of your God too. And are not those
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154435:2"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:154435:3"/>prodigious and Dyabolicall Votes, which will not suffer you to enjoy Heaven, or Earth, or the blessings of either.</p>
            <p>Hence againe we are to be instructed, that these Votes of that Privie Counsell (now set up to outface our Parliament) are a meere scandall and Libell against our Parliament, and deserve to have an eternall brand of infamy set upon them. What a private Juncto or Affembly (for I would faine allow them to be something) stand in opposition to a Parliament? out upon it, for shame leave off your Voting, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity will blush to heare it. Or if you will Vote at adventure &amp; contradict a good conscience for feare of a Female frowne, or a Gibbet jogging you at the elbo, you must then give me leave to tell you, that this is not <hi>Parlar la ment;</hi> but a forced scandalous illegall suffrage, which cannot passe <hi>Nemine contradicente.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to passe my Vote upon yours (for I thinke both equally beare the badge of Authority) and to beginne with the Title; <hi>Ʋotes at Oxford.</hi> It is not told you by whom, whether by that Anti-ck Parliament, or by Her Majesty (the new created thing of <hi>Yarmouth</hi> being also privie and consenting) or by <hi>Bristow, Cottington,</hi> and <hi>Digby,</hi> with the rest of the Spaniolised and Papisticall Faction; or by the Court Mad-Dames (who I must tell you have great share in the Votes at <hi>Oxford</hi>) or in fine whether by part of the Juncto for the whole, for it is most certaine, many of them Vote by an implicite faith, and so beleeve and Vote what they understand not, others Vote by restraint and compultion, and so Vote what they would not. But be the Votes made by whom they will, they are the Votes at <hi>Oxford,</hi> (and hee shall be mounted a story higher that dare contradict it.) But what if this Juncto be composed and made up of Lords, Ladies, and others, as common as themselves, who joyne in Vote; suppose for the raising of men and money, must this binde the honest Subjects of <hi>Oxford:</hi> Resolved upon the Question, that it must; and hee that dabes oppose it, shall have his fortune advanced above the Gates of the City; and is not this a most exact and ready way for the raising of men for Her Majesties service.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It is resolved that the Subiects of</hi> Scotland <hi>who consented to the Declaration of that Kingdome concerning the present expedition into</hi> England, <hi>have denounced warre against the Kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>and broke the Act of Pacification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How, have denounced <hi>Warre</hi> against the Kingdom of <hi>England?</hi> What a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox is this; I would have this Assembly understand, that our Brethren the <hi>Scots</hi> know when they have a warrantable authority for their advance; when not; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they ignorant, what it is to denounce <hi>Warre</hi> against this Kingdom, what not. To be sent for by a Parliament, and to come in their aide; and yet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>Warr</hi> against them; by one and the same Act to fight for, and against, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be made good by <hi>Berkenhead,</hi> no not by all the Sophistry at <hi>Oxford.</hi> But the truth is, they have therefore denounced <hi>Warre</hi> against this Kingdom, and broke the Act of Pacification; for that they refused the rich tender of the addition of many <hi>English</hi> Counties, to their Territories, and the magnificent plunder of this Citie, and would not for so large a reward, take up armes against the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154435:3"/>which would consequently tend to their own destruction; this (if any thing) is the breach of the Act of pacification. But had they come at his Majesties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and taken up armes against the King and Parliament, this had bin no breach of the Act of pacification, vary but the persons, take but the King from his Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, (by whom he ought to be advised) and joyne him with a Privy Counsell (with whom he ought not to consult) and then let the Act or Vote be what it will, and who will submit thereunto, all is lawfull. But be advised to spare your Votes, least you corrupt the Ayre, and be inforced to desert the <hi>Oxford</hi> Clymate. And know this, that our Brethren the <hi>Scots,</hi> are so well advised and satisfied in consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the truth, and integrity of their action, that it is not all the breath in the Convocation at <hi>Oxford,</hi> can Vote them backe againe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Resolved, That all such of the Subjects of</hi> Scotland <hi>as have in a Hostile manner entred into the Towne of</hi> Barwick <hi>upon</hi> Twede, <hi>have thereby broke the Act of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot enter into my most serious thoughts which way the Privie Councell at <hi>Oxford</hi> could make this resolution; without it were upon this ground, that because by that Act they were not to invade this Kingdome as Rebels and Traytors, that therefore they might not come (being sent for) as friends. Or I rather beleeve that they have made this construction upon that Act, (for they at <hi>Oxford</hi> are excellent at corrupting of Texts) that the King may send for them, to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst himselfe and his Parliament, and if they shall then enter the Towne of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> this is no breach of the Act of Pacification; <hi>Mandat Rex,</hi> that is a sufficient Supersedeas to that Act; But if the King and Parliament shall send for them to take up Armes in defence of His Majesty, their Lawes and Liberties, and they then enter <hi>Barwicke,</hi> there the Act is infringed: So that the truth is, the King may doe whatsoever his will leades him to, but the King and Parliament nothing. And this is but the old Prelaticall designe still driven on, to advance the King above his Lawes and Parliament, that His Majesty may be all, and his people nothing. But I hope ere long the Scots will put you quite besides your Voting, and instruct you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, in the language of their Cannon, what it is to breake the Act of Pacification-</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Resolved, That His Majesties Subjects of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales <hi>are by their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and the Act of Pacification bound to resist and suppresse the</hi> Scotts, <hi>&amp;c. as Traytors and Enemies to the State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Did ever men play fast and loose as you doe at <hi>Oxford;</hi> their voluntary entring the Kingdome in defence of their Religion and Liberties, against that Tyranny that the Prelacy had caused to bee exercised over them, by the judgement of this Parliament (of which you were once part) did not intitle them Traytors or Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the State: and are they now to be opposed and resisted as Traytors, when they have the authority of the King and Parliament for their justification. No Traytors if they enter the Kingdome by their owne power and authority, or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the command of His Majesty, but if they enter by the authority and command
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154435:4"/>of the King and Parliament, then they are Traytors and Enemies to the State; very good Doctrine; what will not this Juncto at <hi>Oxford</hi> Vote? since neither Law nor Reason can worke upon their judgements. But what affinity or relation betwixt a Parliament and a Convocation? pray sirs, you that are the pretended Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> if a man should make so bold with your Wisedomes, as to interrogate you, what you conceave of those Irish blood-suckers that were sent for over (through your advice) whether they bee Traytors and Enemies to the State or not? what would you say? I am confident your judgement would make this reply, that they are His Majesties good and loyall Subjects, my and you would Vote them so too, contrary to your Votes and Resolutions this very Parliament; and yet His Majesties most faithfull Subjects the <hi>Scotts,</hi> are by your Votes Traytors and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the State. O the horrid corruption of these men that stop their eyes against cleare light, and will not suffer either King or people to be undeceaved. Well it is resolved that <hi>Newcastle</hi> (that <hi>quondam</hi> Prince of the North) dares not resist the <hi>Scotts,</hi> but is plotting and contriving which way hee may most conveniently and securely steale from them. And it is further resolved upon the question, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever shall dare to resist or oppose them (notwithstanding the Vote of the thing at <hi>Oxford</hi>) shall be handsomely and most exactly beaten for their paines.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Resolved, That all such, &amp;c. that shall be abetting, aiding, and assisting the</hi> Scotts, <hi>&amp;c. shall be deemed and taken as Traytors and Enemies to the State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing that neither your strength nor pollicy can prevaile to worke us out of our Religion and Liberties, doe you thinke that your breaths or Paper Votes can affrighten us? That what the Thundering of Proclamations and ingenious Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells of Declarations cannot do, that your Votes will accomplish? No Sirs, the <hi>Scots</hi> in spight of opposition) advance still nearer and nearer towards <hi>Oxford,</hi> and find more ayders and assisters every day then other, who intend with all convenient speede to visite you, and if at their approach, they shall finde you thus doing, your condition will be very miserable; therefore take this wholesome advice (whilst there is hopes of mercy) repent, recant, and repeale your Votes (wee know you have liberty of conscience to say any thing) that the <hi>Scotts</hi> friends may prove yours, and these may not be your severe Judges hereafter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Resolved, That all His Majesties Subjects of</hi> Scotland, <hi>are bound by the Act of Pacification to resist and represse all of that Kingdome that already have raised Armes or shall rise in Armes to invade this Kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>or Dominion, of</hi> Wales.</p>
            <p>I here is one of the <hi>Oxford</hi> Stratagems, which they have digged as deepe as Hell for; divide and overcome, t'is the Devills Maxime; before they labour to set us against our Brethren (whom posterity will ever honour for their zeale to the common cause) and now they approach nearer home, and indeavour (as much as lyeth in the power of their Votes, which is nothing) to make them dash one against
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154435:4"/>another. No underminding treacherous attempt left unassaid, whereby they migh possibly divide us from our Brethren, our Brethren from us, or our selves fromt one another. Well, goe on brave Spirits, and prosper; Let not the policy of the Enemy disunite you one from another; by a strange perswasion that you are bound to cutt one anothers throates, because no body else will doe it for you, but let their spleene (which they belch out against you) be a ground of courage unto you, and their Votes make you vow sincerity, celerity, and constancy in this great worke; and so Heaven blesse you and preserve you in the day of Battell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>These Votes passed all</hi> Nemine contradicente.</p>
            <p>Which if true is very remarkeable; and very rare, that so many Votes should passe such a number as they say the pretended Parliament is at Oxford without the contradiction of any one person; but the truth is, I never knew any unlawfull as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semly, but hangs together; there is a combination of evill in it; nay there is a bond of brotherhood in evill, which is not easily broken. And this casts shame in our faces, that wee should not be as firmely and as indissolubly united in a good cause, as they at Oxford are in a bad one; who because the enemie cannot destroy us, cast down our selves by our own perfidious treacheries. Not a Vote at Oxford, but passes none contradicting. Let them but put it to the Vote whether wee shall have Superstition and Popery in the Church; or absolute Monarcy &amp; Tyranny in the State, it is presently resolved affirmatively <hi>Nemine contradicente.</hi> Would the King be supplied with plate and money for to buy Armes and Ammunition for to destroy his good Subjects; Let them but put it to the Vote which way this shall bee done, the loane of a hundered thousand pounds passes forthwith: <hi>Nemine contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente,</hi> to be raised by way of Privy Seale; upon which the Subject may subscribe, so much I gave to his Majestie; this is the old private way of pillageing the Subjects purses out of Parliament, and doth the pretended Parliament turne plunderers too? Doth his Majestie want men, &amp; those such as would kill his good Subjects after an exact methodicall, extraordinary manner, Let them but put it to the Vote (if Papists here in England will not serve turne) it presently passes <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi> that so many thousands of barbarus cruell bloodthirsty rebells shall be conveighed ouer into England, to finish that horred Tragedy here, which they have begun in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Thus you see their constancy &amp; unity, that nothing passes the Juncto with the least contradiction. A good lesson for us at London, and so I passe to their Vote<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon our Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved upon the question,</hi> Nemine contradicente.</p>
            <p>Here they combine together against England, as well as <hi>Scotland,</hi> and hope (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they leave convocating) to Vote them both unquestionable miserable. But let them know, that shall never be accomplshed, <hi>Nemine contradicente.</hi> No wee doubt not but our Parliament will ere long Vote down that Privy Counsell, that convocation, that Junto, that Conventicle, that what you will at Oxford. The result</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:154435:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lords and Commons now remaining at Westminster that have given their Vote or consents to the raising of Forces under the Earle of</hi> Essex <hi>or have been abetting, ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or assisting thereunto, have levied and made warr against the King, and are therein guilty of high Treason:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Lords and Commons now remaining at Westminster &amp;c. Are guilty of high Treason;</hi> not those that were there, and Voted or consented to the raising of Forces who since departed this world, and are gone to <hi>Oxford,</hi> No, these are not within the Verge of this Vote; these are not guilty of high Treason; what they guilty of high Treason at Oxford? no, by no meanes. Tis his Majesties best and most loyall Subjects now remaining at Westminster who only beare the burthen of that Vote, Yet by the way let me tell them, that then had the honour to be Members of our Parliament, and are now admitted private Votaries of that thing at Oxford t'will not be safe confiding in your Bretheren of the Junto; discontents, jealousies, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or emulation may court you; and then you at Oxford shall be Voted Traitors as well as wee, for had you been guilty of any such crime, tis not the Oxford aire can purge you. Here we may see the Judgement of these men; that it is not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting to the raising of Forces, but the remaining at Westminstet, that makes our worthies (in their sufferages) guilty of Treason, let them but step aside to betray both King and Country, kisse her Majesties hand, or ingratiate themselves with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery</hi> of <hi>Yarmouth, Digby,</hi> or any other of her Majesties Servants to the quicke; they shall <hi>Ipso facto</hi> be Voted into the Assembly; where if they will joyne in the Voting in of Superstition and Popery, the Voting down of our Parliaments, Lawes and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; and the Voting up and extolling of an exorbitant illegall Prerogative, against all rule and reason, then they shall be no more Traitors, but his Majesties best and most loyall Subjects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved that the Lords and Commons now remaining at Westminster that have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven their votes and consents for the making and using of a new great Seale, have thereby counterfeited the Kings great Seale, and therein committed high Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All their Resolutions run with the same currant; <hi>The Lords and Commons re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining at Westminster;</hi> I, that is their plaguc indeed, that they still remaine at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster;</hi> and wee trust shall doe, when there will not be the least relique of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation at <hi>Oxford.</hi> But now the great Seale prickes their consciences; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got this Vote. Do you thinke that it was not high time to make a new great Seale, when that the old one cared not into whose custody it came, nor what it did? while <hi>Endymion</hi> that quagmire or over-growne peece of iniquity was Keeper, what Popish, Prelaticall, Jesuiticall papers or Proclamations were then issued forth? as if the great Seale it selfe had resolved, to stampe nothing but Popery in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. How were our worthies, for their indefatagable care and labour, for esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing of the Throne in honour and renowne, and for settling of a trve under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing betwixt his Majestie and his people; and uniting of them both in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154435:5"/>peace and affection one towards another; traduced and scandalised as Rebells and Traitors to the King and Kingdome? when as those cruell unparalelled mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strous rebels of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who have dethroned his Majesty and barbarously and most inhumanly massacred and destroyed his people, (the only wealth and honour of a Prince,) were invited over by Commission under the great Seale, to act the like in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity here, by the amicable appellations of his good and loyall Subjects. Wee could also tell you of illegall Commissions of Array that Issued forth under the great Seale, but this doth sufficiently attest, that the old Seale was growne very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, &amp; had entred into the yeares of dotage, &amp; therfore it was high time to make a new one. And if it be high Treason for the Parliament to make a new great Seale, a more then probable meanes of preserving of our Religion and Liberties, of the Kings Majestie, and his dominions from that distruction threatned by the old Seale, then are the Parliament highly guilty of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved, that the Lords and Commons who have given their consents, or have been abetting, ayding, or assisting to the comming in of the</hi> Scots, &amp;c. <hi>have there in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted high Treason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you see it is made a trisle to Vote a whole Parliament at once Traytors; though it passes Law and reason to maintaine it. And is it Treason for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to require the aid of the <hi>Scots</hi> in the defence of King and Parliament? what then is it in those that Counselled and advised His Majestie to call for their assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, with the ingagement of so great reward (who had more Religion then to be so fettered) to fight against &amp; oppose (under a faire coulour and spetious pretence of fighting for) the King and parliament? I, what then are they, that advised his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie to make that bloody and fatall pacification in <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp; to call thence those savadge rebells to act their buchery here, that they might the more speedily and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly finish the losse and destruction of both Kingdomes? Is it Treason to call friends into the Kingdome, and is it not treason to call Rebells? Therefore be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monished O thou thing of <hi>Oxford</hi> to rejudge review thy former resolutions, to see whether thou canst make them run paralell with the rule of reason and sound judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved that the Lords and Commons &amp;c. Who have committed the crime mentioned in the three former Votes, have therein broken the trust reposed in them by their Country &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I here is the old engine and the very Epitome and abstract of mischiefe againe revived, can they but infuse or insinuate this into the hearts of the people, that our worthies of Parliament have infringed the trust reposed in them by their Country, then all is their own. Sirs doe but beleeve this, and you shall quickly be made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments of your own ruine: you shall purchase your faith, with the plunder of your Coffers, and the destruction of this City and Kingdome. Is the raising of an <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> under the Earle of <hi>Essex:</hi> the making of a new great Seale, &amp; the bringing in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154435:6"/>of our Bretheren the Scots; and all, in the defence of the Kings Majesties person and just power, our Religion, Lawes, and Liberties, a breach of the trust reposed in them by their Country? if ever this doctrin be received or approved of by others then by Papists, Atheists, and Ignorant seduced Brittaines; I'le be their bond slaves that preach it, if that be a breach of trust, let the best and most sage Headpeeces in Oxford resolve me (if they can) what is an execution of it. Sirs wee are to well grounded in our experience and beleefe to bee catcht with such weake and obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oussnares as these are; tis not your Votes can intangle us: such as have approved themselves loyall and faithfull to God, their King, and Country, shall (let the mouth of malice open never so wide against them) be honoured and renowned to all posterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Resolved that all the endeavours and offers of peace and Treaty made by his Majestie, by the advise of the Lords and Commons of Parliament, assembled at Oxford, have been refused and rejected by the Lords and commons remaining at Westminster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No wonder if such offers and tenders of peace returne empty handed and loose their errant, if they come with such inscriptions as these are, <hi>by the advise of the Lords and Commons of Parliament assembled at Oxford;</hi> what such as are impeached for Treason, such as have not only broken the trust reposed in them by their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, by their absence, but also by their evill Counsells; such as have either actually and in their own persons, levied warr against the Parliament, or have been Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selling, abetting, ayding, or assisting therunto; what such still Lords &amp; Commons of Parliament: can it be thought by the most common understanding, that these men ever expected to see or injoy, what they pretended to desire? it cannot be imagined. No, the Junto knows how to qualifie their demands, so that they may return ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall. They know what seemingly to require, I and when and after what method too, which they neither can, nor would have granted: or at least not after that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that tis requested. They offer impossibilities, when they would court &amp; decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve the vulgar by tenders of peace; which to some (through the poverty and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the times) seemes sweete, though never so unreasonable. <hi>Dulce nomen pacis;</hi> the very name of peace savours sweete in the time of warr. And the truth is, tis no wonder if people so much desire it, for it is the very <hi>Cornucopia</hi> of all terrene &amp; sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary happines; and therefore may he perish; may a perpetuall Warr in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science be his Curse, who desiers not so great a blessing. But know, that relapses are most dangerous, and therefore under the disguise and Visard of peace, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to that which may increase our flame, and reduce us to a much worse conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereafter, farre be it from us. Wherefore let them Vote our refusall of the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Peace; thereby hoping to recrute their Forces (for you must know they seeke their owne, not the Common good,) I doubt not their increase will be as small, as their hopes are great; pollicy against God never yet prevailed. If you would have Peace, seeke it in the right way; we will with all our soules joyne with you, otherwise may Warre be our Portion.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>